

Afshin Rahimi

Research Interests

My research interests fall within the fields of Natural Language Processing, Social Network Analysis and Machine Learning. I am specifically interested in exploiting both structured and unstructured data to help machines understand human language in Emergency Situations and Health Informatics.

Education

2014–2018 PhD in Computer Science, The University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Australia.

Thesis: Analysing the Interplay of Location, Language and Links Utilising Geotagged Twitter

2010–2013 **MSc. Computational Linguistics**, *Sharif University of Technology*, Tehran, Iran.

Thesis: An Information Theoretic Analysis of Phonetic Sequences, The Case of Sonority.

2002–2006 BSc. Computer Science, Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran.

Thesis: Authorship Attribution of Persian Texts.

Academic Activities

Reviewing Reviewed for ACL, EMNLP, EACL and Transactions of Information Systems.

Teaching

- Tutor for Graduate Statistical Machine Learning, Unimelb, 2018
- Tutor for Database Systems, Newman College, 2018.
- Tutor for Database Systems, Newman College, 2017.
- Tutor for Cloud Computing, Newman College, 2017.
- Demonstrator for Undergraduate Machine Learning, Unimelb, 2017.

Organisation

- o Co-organiser for W-NUT Workshop 2016, 2018.
- Remote Presentation Chair for ACL 2018.

Student

- Supervision PhD Advisory Committee Member of Yimeng Dai, Unimelb, 2018.
 - PhD Advisory Committee Member of Yiqing Zhang, Unimelb, 2018.

Thesis

- Examination Master Thesis Examiner, Unimelb, 2018.
 - Master Thesis Examiner, Unimelb, 2018.

Publications

- to appear Dirk Hovy, Afshin Rahimi, Timothy Baldwin, and Julian Brooke. Visualizing regional language variation across europe on twitter. Handbook of the Changing World Language Map, to appear.
 - 2018 Wei Xu, Alan Ritter, Tim Baldwin, and Afshin Rahimi. Proceedings of the 2018 emnlp workshop w-nut: The 4th workshop on noisy user-generated text. In Proceedings of the 2018 EMNLP Workshop W-NUT: The 4th Workshop on Noisy User-generated Text, 2018.
 - 2018 Afshin Rahimi. Analysing the interplay of location, language and links utilising geotagged Twitter content. PhD thesis, 2018.
 - 2018 Taro Miyazaki, Afshin Rahimi, Trevor Cohn, and Timothy Baldwin. geolocation using knowledge-based methods. In Proceedings of the 2018 EMNLP Workshop W-NUT: The 4th Workshop on Noisy User-generated Text, pages 7-16,
 - 2018 Timothy Baldwin, Trevor Cohn, and Afshin Rahimi. Semi-supervised user geolocation via graph convolutional networks. In Proceedings of the 56th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, ACL 2018, Melbourne, Australia, July 15-20, 2018, Volume 1: Long Papers, pages 2009-2019, 2018.
 - 2017 Afshin Rahimi, Trevor Cohn, and Timothy Baldwin. A neural model for user geolocation and lexical dialectology. In Proceedings of the 55th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2017), 2017.
 - 2017 Afshin Rahimi, Trevor Cohn, and Timothy Baldwin. Continuous representation of location for geolocation and lexical dialectology using mixture density networks. In Proceedings of the Proceedings of the 2017 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2017) (to appear), 2017.
 - 2016 Afshin Rahimi, Trevor Cohn, and Timothy Baldwin. pigeo: A python geotagging tool. Proceedings of ACL-2016 System Demonstrations, pages 127–132, 2016.
 - 2015 Afshin Rahimi, Duy Vu, Trevor Cohn, and Timothy Baldwin. Exploiting text and network context for geolocation of social media users. In Proceedings of the 2015 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics — Human Language Technologies (NAACL HLT 2015), Denver, USA, 2015.
 - 2015 Afshin Rahimi, Trevor Cohn, and Timothy Baldwin. Twitter user geolocation using a unified text and network prediction model. Proceedings of the 53rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics — 7th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (ACL-IJCNLP 2015), 2015.

Work Experience

04/2018-now Research Fellow in NLP, Melbourne University, Melbourne, Australia.

I've joined the NLP group at the University of Melbourne, working on NLP for low-resource languages as part of the Ariel project supervised by Trevor Cohn. Currently I'm working on NER for low-resource languages using transfer from multiple source languages.

2016–2017 Internship (4months), TELSTRA TELCO, Melbourne, Australia.

My internship was on customer intent prediction in interactive voice response (IVR) systems based on historical events (website visits, previous calls). My work involved working with technologies like GreenPlum and Theano to create learning models that can predict the intent of a customer (e.g. talking about billing, a problem with their Smart TV service or a failing modem) from their previous events (e.g. page visit, previous calls, previous bill) which improved routing of customers to agents resulting customer satisfaction and cost reduction. The CTO of the company mentioned the results of my work in a general meeting and supported the investment of the company in the same line of work to improve customer experience.

2013–2014 Researcher, LINNEAUS UNIVERSITY, Stockholm, Sweden.

I was responsible for Text Analytics components of a projects which focused on study of stance/sentiment in big data real-time text streams like Twitter. My job involved Information Retrieval, working on Vector Space Models, Feature Extraction and Classification/Clustering of Stance/Sentiment in real time big data streams.

2011–2013 Java Developer, MITRC, Tehran, Iran.

I was responsible for a team of 4 developers working on the crawler component of a large scale web search engine. I could improve the crawler's performance from just 1 million fetched URLs to 1 billion at the end. The crawler had about 2 billion URLs where 1 billion ones were fetched and updated regularly. The data was about 30 TB. We used Hadoop's HDFS, MapReduce and HBase. We built our web crawler on top of Apache Nutch an open source popular web crawler.

2006–2011 **Software Developer and System Administrator**, KECO, Tehran, Iran.

Main responsibilities include: Software Development (Web and Desktop) using .NET (C# and ASP) and MSSQL. Cisco Switching Administrator (50+ access switches and 4 distribution switches in a 2 tier network architecture, 500+ nodes, vlan, portsec, spanning-tree, redundancy, architecture, load balancing, high-availability), Windows Network Administrator (Active Directory, High Availability, Centralised Management), ERP Administrator (Supply Chain, Salary, HR), Microsoft SQL Server Administrator and Developer. I learned to work with technology under heavy pressure where a medium sized company (2k+ users) relies on your design and administration 24/7.

Technical skills

NLP Expertise in Core NLP tasks (e.g. tagging, Parsing, ASR, LM, MT)

Machine Expertise in Deep Learning, Supervised, Low-resource and Unsupervised Learning. Learning

Graph Mining Experienced in data collection (e.g. from Twitter), data curation to create datasets, graph construction, and graph analysis algorithms (e.g. node classification)

Collaboration Git, SVN, JIRA, GreenHopper

Big Data Experienced in Hadoop MapReduce, NoSQL and Hive, Familiar with Spark

Database MS/My/Posgre SQL, GreenPlum, HBase, Lucene

Network Cisco Switching Design and Maintenance

887 Swanston st. – Parkville, Victoria 3052, Australia

☑ afshinrahimi@gmail.com • 'the afshinrahimi.github.io

Residential Status: Permanent Resident

Programming Experienced in Python and Java

OS Linux

Languages

English Equal to IELTS 8 in all skills

Persian Native

Honours and Awards

- 2017 My paper on geolocation was selected to be presented in the outstanding session in $ACL\ 2017$.
- 2015 Awarded Melbourne University's Travel Scholarship to attend NAACL 2015 conference.
- 2015 Awarded Google's Travel Scholarship to attend ACL 2015 conference.
- 2014 Awarded Australia's government scholarship (IPRS) for PhD studies in The University of Melbourne.
- 2013 Graduated as the top student of the M.Sc. program in Computational Linguistics from Sharif U. of Tech.
- 2002 Ranked 241st among more than 500k high school students in national entrance exam for universities in Iran.

References

Tim Baldwin My PhD supervisor at The University of Melbourne. tb@ldwin.net

Trevor Cohn My PhD supervisor at The University of Melbourne. t.cohn@unimelb.edu.au